Rabinowitch, Eugene I.; Papers ger075
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Eugene I. Rabinowitch Papers
1923-1973
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ger075
14 cubic ft.
Russian-born chemist and SUNY Albany professor who worked on the Manhattan Project, was an early leader of the Concerned Scientists Movement, and helped organize the Pugwash Conferences on Science and World Affairs. The Rabinowitch Papers document various aspects of his life and career and contain his writings, his involvement with the Pugwash Conferences and the Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists, his research interests in photosynthesis, and his work at the University of Illinois and the State University of New York at Albany.
Biographical Sketch
Eugene I. Rabinowitch was born on April 27, 1901 at St. Petersburg, Russia, the son of Isaac and Zinaida (Weinlud) Rabinowitch. In 1921 Isaac Rabinowitch, a lawyer, moved his family to Berlin to escape the Russian persecution of Jews. Eugene Rabinowitch attended the University of Berlin, earning there his doctorate in chemistry in 1926. After serving as an assistant in physical chemistry at the Kaiser Wilhelm Institute, Rabinowitch went to the University of Göttingen where he was a research associate in physics from 1929 to 1933. With the rise of the Nazi Party in the early 1930s, Jews, such as Rabinowitch, were expelled from their university posts. With the loss of his fellowship Rabinowitch was forced to leave Germany.
Rabinowitch with his wife, Anya Mejerson, whom he married on March 12, 1932, went first to Copenhagen to work with Neils Bohr at the Institute of Theoretical Physics. From here Rabinowitch moved to London to work with F. G. Donnan at University College. Rabinowitch remained in London from 1934 to 1938. It was here that his twin sons, Alexander and Victor, were born on August 30, 1934.
In 1938 Rabinowitch was invited to the United States to lecture. This resulted in the offer of a position with the Cabot Solar Energy Research Project at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Rabinowitch was at MIT from 1939 to 1944, when James Franck, a former colleague from Göttingen, invited him to come to Chicago. In Chicago Rabinowitch joined Franck and several other distinguished scientists at what was being called the Metallurgical Laboratory. This was in reality one of the principal research centers of the Manhattan Project. Rabinowitch worked with the Project from 1944 until its completion in 1946, serving as senior chemist and section chief of the Metallurgical Laboratory's Information Division.
In June 1945 Rabinowitch and physicist Leo Szilard authored a memorandum, which became known as the Franck Report. The memorandum, which argued against the military use of the atomic bomb, was signed by seven Metallurgical Laboratory scientists led by Franck and was personally carried by Franck to the government in Washington, D. C. Although it did not persuade the United States government to refrain from use of the atomic bomb without prior demonstration of its capabilities, the Franck Report is one of the earliest statements of the Concerned Scientists Movement of the 1940s and 1950s. This Movement, which marshalled the talent and dedication of several of the scientists who had worked on the atomic bomb, was born out of the scientists' conviction that the scientific community had a right, if not a duty, to speak out on the new and complicated policy issues of the nuclear age. Joined by many colleagues who had not worked on the atomic bomb but who shared their concern, these scientists worked to educate the American public and government about the significance of atomic power. Rabinowitch was an early leader in both the Movement and the educational effort, co-founding with Hyman Goldsmith the Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists. As the editor-in-chief for more than twenty years Rabinowitch maintained the Bulletin's quality and independence as a forum for discussion of scientific issues with social and political implications. As such it reflected Rabinowitch's belief in the importance of keeping the scientific community informed about the impact on society of the twentieth century scientific and technological revolution in which it played a significant part.
In addition to his work on the Bulletin and his participation in organizations of the Scientist's Movement, Rabinowitch continued to teach, to write, and to pursue his research interests in the field of photosynthesis. His seminal scientific work, Photosynthesis and Related Processes, was published in three parts between 1945 and 1956 and was supplemented by numerous articles on the topic. In 1947 Rabinowitch joined the faculty of the University of Illinois at Urbana as a research professor of botany. Helping to organize the University's Photosynthesis Research Laboratory, he then served as its director. From 1966 to 1968 he was also a member of the University's Center for Advanced Studies.
Rabinowitch's interest in public policy and political affairs was demonstrated in 1955, when he helped to organize the international forum, which became known as the Pugwash Conferences on Science and World Affairs. Initiated in response to increasing world tension, the Pugwash Conferences grew out of the hopes of many distinguished scientists that war could be eliminated as an instrument of foreign policy. The Russell-Einstein Manifesto, calling for the peaceful discussion of scientific issues in an apolitical arena, sparked the convening of the first Pugwash meeting in 1957. Named for the site of the first conference, Pugwash, Nova Scotia, the international meetings provide natural and social scientists with the opportunity to discuss policy issues with their colleagues from around the world. Rabinowitch, a founder of the organization, served as a member of the International Continuing Committee of Pugwash from 1957 to 1973 and was president of the movement from 1969 to 1970.
In 1968 Rabinowitch retired from the University of Illinois and took a position with the State University of New York at Albany as professor of biology and chemistry and as senior advisor to the newly-established Center for Science and the Future of Human Affairs (later called the Center for the Study of Science and Society). Rabinowitch was the guiding force behind the new Center working to obtain funds for it and establishing goals and objectives for it. The Center was to reflect Rabinowitch's own concerns with the way in which science and technology impacted on society. Rabinowitch's son, Victor, was director of the Center from 1968 to 1970. Following Victor's resignation, Eugene Rabinowitch served as acting director from March to September 1970. Rabinowitch retired from SUNY at Albany on August 31, 1972 and was immediately reappointed as a visiting professor for the 1972/1973 school year. At this time Rabinowitch was given a leave of absence from the University in order to accept a fellowship with the Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars of the Smithsonian Institute. While in Washington, he continued to write, edit the Bulletin, and participate in Pugwash. Eugen I. Rabinowitch died on May 15, 1973 at Washington, D. C., at the age of seventy-two.
Books by Rabinowitch:
1928 Rare Gases
1930 Periodic System
1945 Photosynthesis and Related Processes, Volume I
1950 Minutes to Midnigh t, editor
1950 Photosynthesis and Related Processes, Volume II, Part I
1951 The Chemistry of Uranium, with J. J. Katz
1956 Photosynthesis and Related Processes, Volume II, Part II
1963 The Atomic Age, edited with Morton Grodzins
1964 The Dawn of a New Age
1964 Spectroscopy and Photochemistry of Uranyl Compounds, with.R. Linn Belford
1969 Mau on the Moon, edited with Richard Lewis
1969 Photosynthesis, with Govindjee
1975 Views of Science, Technology and Development, edited with Victor Rabinowitch
Awards Received by Rabinowitch:
1955 Guggenheim Fellowship
1960 D.H. L., Brandeis University (honorary)
1964 Dr. Sci., Dartmouth College (honorary)
1966 Kalinga Prize, United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization (for popularization of science)
1967 Columbia College, Chicago
1970 Dr. Sci., Alma College, Michigan
1972 American Academy of Arts and Sciences (award for promotion of international cooperation among scientists)
1972 Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars Fellowship
Scope and Contents
The Eugene I. Rabinowitch Papers, 1923-1973, document various aspects of the life and career of Rabinowitch. The papers concern his writings, his involvement with the Pugwash Conferences and the Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists, his research interests in photosynthesis, and his work at the University of Illinois and the State University of New York at Albany.
The papers date primarily from 1968 to 1972 when Rabinowitch was a member of the faculty at the State University of New York at Albany. A small amount of earlier material concerns Rabinowitch's writings and his editorship of the Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists. The researcher is also referred to collections of Rabinowitch papers held by the University of Illinois Archives and the University of Chicago Library. In addition, please see the papers of the Center for the Study of Science and Society, also held by the SUNYA University Archives.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into seven series.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, in 1981 by Dr. Victor Rabinowitch, son of Dr. Eugene Rabinowitch.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Bulletin of the Atomic Scientist.; Rabinowitch, Eugene, 1901-1973.; American Academy of Arts and Sciences.
- Correspondence, 1945-1973; 1
  Scope and Contents
  Consists of general correspondence and subject files dating primarily from 1968 to 1972. The incoming and outgoing correspondence is arranged alphabetically by name of individual, name of organization, or subject. A general file for each letter of the alphabet precedes other files for the same letter of the alphabet (ie.: "A" precedes "American Institute of Chemists"). Items within the files are arranged chronologically by year, month, and day. Partially dated items are placed at the end of the month or year; undated items are placed after dated material. Enclosures are placed after their letter of transmittal. The correspondence concerns a wide range of Rabinowitch's interests including his publications, his lectures, and his work as a teacher and researcher. Files relating to the Atomic Energy Commission, the National Science Foundation, and the Research Foundation of the State University of New York document Rabinowitch's research in the field of photosynthesis and the grants, which supported this research. Rabinowitch's interest in the relation of science and technology to public policy and international affairs is detailed in his correspondence files with men such as Hubert H. Humphrey and Frank Church as well as files such as those concerning the Sakharov Memorandum or the Emergency Committee of Atomic Scientists.
  - A, 1947 October-1972 June; Undated (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 1)
  - Air Force Office of Scientific Research, 1968 January-1969 March (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 2)
  - Alma College, 1970 February-1970 June (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 3)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1961 September-1969 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 4)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1970 January-1972 June (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 5)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1970 December-1972 June (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 6)
  - American Institute of Chemists, 1968 October-1972 February; Undated (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 7)
  - Association of Oak Ridge Engineers and Scientists, 1948 September (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 8)
  - Atomic Energy Commission, Correspondence, 1964 November-1969 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 9)
  - Atomic Energy Commission, Grants, Financial Reports, 1965 July-1968 June (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 10)
  - Atomic Energy Commission, Grants, Proposals, 1966 May-1969 April (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 11)
  - Atomic Energy Commission, Press Releases, 1947 May-1948 January (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 12)
  - Atomic Energy Commission, Press Releases, 1948 February-1948 September (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 13)
  - B, 1954 May-1972 June (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 14)
  - Bauer, Richard K., 1970 January-1971 November (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 15)
  - Bay, Ray, Jr., 1964 July-1969 May (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 16)
  - Biographical Material, 1958 April-1973 June (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 17)
  - Biophysical Society, 1970 July-1971 March; Undated (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 18)
  - British Information Services, 1945 August (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 19)
  - C, 1945 September-1972 May; Undated (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 20)
  - Campa, Riccardo, Nuova Antologia, 1968 November-1969 August (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 21)
  - Center for Advanced Study in Theology and the Sciences, 1967 January-1972 May (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 22)
  - Church, Frank, 1969 July-1969 December (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 23)
  - Conference on the Status of Soviet Jews, 1970 July (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 24)
  - D, 1968 September-1972 June (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 25)
  - Doubleday and Company, Inc., 1954 July-1955 October (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 26)
  - E, 1966 August-1971 May (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 25)
  - Educational Committee to Halt Atomic Weapons Spread, Undated (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 28)
  - Emergency Committee of Atomic Scientists, 1947 June-1948 January (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 29)
  - F, 1948 April-1972 June (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 30)
  - Financial Planning, 1964 June-1964 August (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 31)
  - Frackowiak, Danuta, 1968 February-1970 August (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 32)
  - Franck, James, 1952 July-1965 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 33)
  - Franck, James, 1966 March-1968 February; Undated (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 34)
  - The Fund for Peace, 1970 January-1971 March (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 35)
  - G, 1945 September-1972 May (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 36)
  - Govindjee, 1968 July-1972 April (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 37)
  - H, 1945 August-1972 May (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 38)
  - Hansen, Kenneth R., 1970 August (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 39)
  - Holifield, Chet, 1947 July-1948 April (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 40)
  - Humphrey, Hubert H., 1966 January-1972 May (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 41)
  - I, 1962 March-1971 April; Undated (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 42)
  - India Trip, 1969 April-1969 November (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 43)
  - Institute on Man and Science, 1965 September-1972 June; Undated (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 44)
  - International Science Foundation, 1969 May-1970 December (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 45)
  - Inter-University Committee on Travel Grants, 1967 August (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 46)
  - J, 1958 July-1971 November; Undated (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 47)
  - Journal of Theoretical Biology, 1971 March-1971 July (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 48)
  - K, 1955 February-1971 August (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 49)
  - Kasha, Michael, 1972 March-1972 May (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 50)
  - Kettering Award, 1969 September-1970 April (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 51)
  - L, 1955 March-1971 December (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 52)
  - Lavorel, J., 1967 April (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 53)
  - M, 1955 August-1972 May; Undated (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 54)
  - McGraw-Hill Book Company, 1954 December-1969 June (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 55)
  - Mar, Ted, 1970 March-1972 April (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 56)
  - Merkelo, Henry, 1968 July-1970 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 57)
  - Minerva, 1966 October-1971 March; Undated (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 58)
  - Miscellaneous, 1968 June-1970 August; Undated (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 59)
  - N, 1955 October-1972 June (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 60)
  - National Aeronautics and Space Administration, 1968 June-1969 June (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 61)
  - National Science Foundation, Grants, Financial Statements, 1968 June-1972 April; Undated (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 1)
  - National Science Foundation, Grants, Proposals, 1968 September-1971 September (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 2)
  - Nobel Peace Prize, 1969 July-1971 September (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 3)
  - North Atlantic Treaty Organization, 1972 January (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 4)
  - O, 1962 March-1972 June (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 5)
  - P, 1963 October-1972 March (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 6)
  - Pantheon Books, 1962 March-1964 July (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 7)
  - Peace Corps, 1964 April (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 8)
  - Pergamon Press, Ltd., 1963 January-1963 March (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 9)
  - Photochemistry and Photobiology, 1968 October-1971 February (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 10)
  - Poremsky, V., 1968 December-1970 February (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 11)
  - R, 1950 March-1971 June (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 12)
  - Rabinowitch, Anya, 1966 (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 13)
  - Research Foundation of the State University of New York, Correspondence, 1968 October-1971 May (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 14)
  - Research Foundation of the State University of New York, Grant, Financial Reports, 1969 February-1971 November (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 15)
  - S, 1950 October-1972 May (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 16)
  - Sakharov Memorandum, Correspondence, 1968 July-1971 March (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 17)
  - Sakharov Memorandum, Clippings, 1969 January-1969 February; Undated (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 18)
  - Scientific American, 1969 January-1972 June (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 19)
  - Shils, Edward, 1971 October-1972 June (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 20)
  - Singhal, Gauri S., 1968 August-1972 June; Undated (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 21)
  - Smaller, Bernard, 1962 August (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 22)
  - Society for Social Responsibility in Science, 1969 September-1970 September (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 23)
  - Stamler Legal Aid Fund, 1969 July-1971 May (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 24)
  - State University of New York at Albany, 1968 April-1971 June; Undated (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 25)
  - Szalay, Lazlo, 1969 September-1971 June (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 26)
  - T, 1958 July-1972 May (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 27)
  - U, 1955 October-1972 May (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 28)
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization, 1967 April-1970 July (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 29)
  - United States Department of Defense, 1948 May (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 30)
  - University of Delhi, 1970 February-1970 November (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 31)
  - University of Illinois, Correspondence, 1962 May-1972 June (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 32)
  - University of Illinois, Division of General Studies, 1966 December-1967 February (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 33)
  - University of Illinois, Interdisciplinary Analysis of Social Issues Course, 1966 August-1968 June (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 34)
  - University of Illinois at Chicago Circle, 1969 October-1970 March (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 35)
  - V, 1966 July (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 36)
  - Vassar College, 1968 October-1968 November (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 37)
  - W, 1958 September-1971 January (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 38)
  - Wald, George, 1968 October-1971 March (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 39)
  - Wang, Richard, 1969 September-1972 February (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 40)
  - Winner, Thomas G., 1969 May-1970 May (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 41)
  - Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars, 1971 June-1971 December (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 42)
  - World Peace Through Law Center, 1969 September (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 43)
  - Z, 1968 November-1971 February (Box 2 (1-Correspondence), Folder 44)
- Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists, 1945-1973; 2
  The Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists (BAS) was begun in December 1945 by Eugene Rabinowitch and Hyman H. Goldsmith. Originally called the Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists of Chicago, it served as a newsletter for the Atomic Scientists of Chicago. In 1946 the name was changed to its present form. The Bulletin started "as a means of calling public attention to the perils of atomic energy and the urgent need for its control by a civilian agency". The BAS evolved into a forum for scientists concerned about science policy and the relationship of science to national and international affairs. It covers topics ranging from genetics to pollution to space exploration. Rabinowitch and Goldsmith co-edited the journal until the latter's death in August 1949. From 1949 until his own death in 1973, Rabinowitch was editor-in-chief of the Bulletin. BAS continues to be published ten times a year under the auspices of the Educational Foundation of Nuclear Science, Inc. The Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists, 1945-1972, files are organized into three sections as listed and described below. Material within the sections is arranged chronologically by year, month, and day. Partially dated material is placed at the end of the month or year; undated items are placed after dated material.
  - Correspondence, 1945-1972; 2.1
    The Correspondence dates primarily from 1964 to 1972. The correspondence with staff and board members details the activities and organization of the BAS. There are also letters from individuals who wished to contribute articles to the journal. Correspondence may also be found from readers commenting on articles in the Bulletin, such as one from Bertrand Russell discussing an editorial on Vietnam by Rabinowitch. Individuals figuring prominently in the activities of the BAS and in the correspondence include:
    Adams, Ruth Managing Editor.
    Betbe, Hans Board of Sponsors.
    Blum, Walter J. Legal Counsel.
    Feld, Bernard T. Board of Directors.
    Goldsmith, Hyman H. Co-founder and Co-editor, 1945-1949.
    Gomer, Robert Editorial Board.
    Grodzins, Ruth Editorial Staff.
    Kalven, Harry, Jr. Board of Directors.
    Lewis, Richard Managing Editor.
    Penn, Virginia Editorial Staff.
    Rabinowitch, Victor Board of Directors.
    Rosen, Eunice Editorial Staff.
    Shils, Edward Editorial Board and Board of Directors.
    Shils, Ruth Editorial Staff.
    - Correspondence, 1945 September-1958 November (Box 2 (2-Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists), Folder 46)
    - Correspondence, 1959 January-1965 (Box 2 (2-Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists), Folder 47)
    - Correspondence, 1966 January-1968 May (Box 2 (2-Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists), Folder 48)
    - Correspondence, 1968 June-1968 December (Box 2 (2-Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists), Folder 49)
    - Correspondence, 1969 January-1969 December (Box 2 (2-Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists), Folder 50)
    - Correspondence, 1970 January-1970 October (Box 2 (2-Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists), Folder 51)
    - Correspondence, 1970 November-1971 December (Box 2 (2-Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists), Folder 52)
    - Correspondence, 1972 January-1972 June; Undated (Box 2 (2-Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists), Folder 53)
  - Administration, 1945-1972; 2.2